TOPIC
    about_Functions_Advanced_Parameters

SHORT DESCRIPTION
    Explains how to add parameters to advanced functions.

LONG DESCRIPTION
    You can add parameters to the advanced functions that you write, and use
    parameter attributes and arguments to limit the parameter values that
    function users submit with the parameter.

    The parameters that you add to your function are available to users in
    addition to the common parameters that Windows PowerShell adds automatically
    to all cmdlets and advanced functions. For more information about the Windows
    PowerShell common parameters, see about_CommonParameters 
    (http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkID=113216).

    Beginning in Windows PowerShell 3.0, you can use splatting with @Args to
    represent the parameters in a command. This technique is valid on simple
    and advanced functions. For more information, see about_Functions
    (http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkID=113231) and about_Splatting
    (http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkID=262720).


Static Parameters
    Static parameters are parameters that are always available in the function.
    Most parameters in Windows PowerShell cmdlets and scripts are static parameters.

    The following example shows the declaration of a ComputerName parameter that
    has the following characteristics:

        - It is mandatory (required).
        - It takes input from the pipeline.
        - It takes an array of strings as input.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
            ValueFromPipeline=$true)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 
  

  Attributes of Parameters
  
    This section describes the attributes that you can add to function
    parameters. 

    All attributes are optional. However, if you omit the CmdletBinding
    attribute, then to be recognized as an advanced function, the function
    must include the Parameter attribute.     

    You can add one or multiple attributes in each parameter declaration. There
    is no limit to the number of attributes that you can add to a parameter
    declaration.


  The Parameter Attribute

      The Parameter attribute is used to declare the attributes of function
      parameters. 
 
      The Parameter attribute is optional, and you can omit it if none of the
      parameters of your functions need attributes, but to be recognized as
      an advanced function (rather than a simple function), a function must have
      either the CmdletBinding attribute or the Parameter attribute, or both.

      The Parameter attribute has arguments that define the characteristics
      of the parameter, such as whether the parameter is mandatory or optional. 

      Use the following syntax to declare the Parameter attribute, an argument,
      and an argument value. The parentheses that enclose the argument and its
      value must follow "Parameter" with no intervening space.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Argument=value)]
            $ParameterName
          ) 


       Use commas to separate arguments within the parentheses. Use the
       following syntax to declare two arguments of the Parameter attribute.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Argument1=value1,
                       Argument2=value2)]

          ) 


       If you use the Parameter attribute without arguments (as an alternative
       to using the CmdletBinding attribute), the parentheses that follow the
       attribute name are still required.

        Param
          (
            [parameter()]
            $ParameterName
          ) 

           

    Mandatory Argument

        The Mandatory argument indicates that the parameter is required. If this
        argument is not specified, the parameter is an optional parameter. 

        The following example declares the ComputerName parameter. It uses the
        Mandatory argument to make the parameter mandatory.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    Position Argument

        The Position argument determines whether the parameter name is required
        when the parameter is used in a command. When a parameter declaration
        includes the Position argument, the parameter name can be omitted and
        Windows PowerShell identifies the unnamed parameter value by its position
        (or order) in the list of unnamed parameter values in the command.
       
        If the Position argument is not specified, the parameter name (or a parameter
        name alias or abbreviation) must precede the parameter value whenever the
        parameter is used in a command. 

        By default, all function parameters are positional. Windows PowerShell 
        assigns position numbers to parameters in the order in which the         
        parameters are declared in the function. To disable this feature,
        set the value of the PositionalBinding argument of the CmdletBinding
        attribute to $False. The Position argument takes precedence over the
        value of the PositionalBinding argument for the parameters on which it
        is declared. For more information, see PositionalBinding in
        about_Functions_CmdletBindingAttribute.
        
        The value of the Position argument is specified as an integer. A position
        value of 0 represents the first position in the command, a position 
        value of 1 represents the second position in the command, and so on. 

        If a function has no positional parameters, Windows PowerShell assigns
        positions to each parameter based on the order in which the parameters
        are declared. However, as a best practice, do not rely on this assignment.
        When you want parameters to be positional, use the Position argument. 

        The following example declares the ComputerName parameter. It uses the
        Position argument with a value of 0. As a result, when "-ComputerName"
        is omitted from command, its value must be the first or only unnamed 
        parameter value in the command.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Position=0)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


        NOTE: When the Get-Help cmdlet displays the corresponding "Position?" parameter
              attribute, the position value is incremented by 1. For example, a parameter
              with a Position argument value of 0 has a parameter attribute of
             "Position? 1."



    ParameterSetName Argument

        The ParameterSetName argument specifies the parameter set to which a 
        parameter belongs. If no parameter set is specified, the parameter 
        belongs to all the parameter sets defined by the function. Therefore, to
        be unique, each parameter set must have at least one parameter that is
        not a member of any other parameter set. 

        The following example declares a ComputerName parameter in the Computer
        parameter set, a UserName parameter in the User parameter set, and a 
        Summary parameter in both parameter sets.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ParameterSetName="Computer")]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName,

            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ParameterSetName="User")]
            [String[]]
            $UserName,

            [parameter(Mandatory=$false)]
            [Switch]
            $Summary
          )

        You can specify only one ParameterSetName value in each argument and only
        one ParameterSetName argument in each Parameter attribute. To indicate that
        a parameter appears in more than one parameter set, add additional Parameter        
        attributes.

        The following example explicitly adds the Summary parameter to the Computer
        and User parameter sets. The Summary parameter is mandatory in one parameter
        set and optional in the other.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ParameterSetName="Computer")]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName,

            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ParameterSetName="User")]
            [String[]]
            $UserName,

            [parameter(Mandatory=$false, ParameterSetName="Computer")]
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true, ParameterSetName="User")]
            [Switch]
            $Summary
          )
        

        For more information about parameter sets, see "Cmdlet Parameter Sets" 
        in the MSDN library at http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkId=142183.


    ValueFromPipeline Argument

        The ValueFromPipeline argument indicates that the parameter accepts 
        input from a pipeline object. Specify this argument if the function 
        accepts the entire object, not just a property of the object. 

        The following example declares a ComputerName parameter that is
        mandatory and accepts an object that is passed to the function
        from the pipeline.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ValueFromPipeline=$true)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    ValueFromPipelineByPropertyName Argument

        The valueFromPipelineByPropertyName argument indicates that the 
        parameter accepts input from a property of a pipeline object. The
        object property must have the same name or alias as the parameter.

        For example, if the function has a ComputerName parameter, and the 
        piped object has a ComputerName property, the value of the ComputerName
        property is assigned to the ComputerName parameter of the function.

        The following example declares a ComputerName parameter that is 
        mandatory and accepts input from the ComputerName property of the 
        object that is passed to the function through the pipeline.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ValueFromPipelineByPropertyName=$true)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    ValueFromRemainingArguments Argument

        The ValueFromRemainingArguments argument indicates that the parameter
        accepts all of the parameters values in the command that are not
        assigned to other parameters of the function. 

        The following example declares a ComputerName parameter that is 
        mandatory and accepts all the remaining parameter values that were 
        submitted to the function.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true,
                      ValueFromRemainingArguments=$true)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    HelpMessage Argument

        The HelpMessage argument specifies a string that contains a brief
        description of the parameter or its value. Windows PowerShell displays
        this message in the prompt that appears when a mandatory parameter value
        is missing from a command. This argument has no effect on optional parameters.

        The following example declares a mandatory ComputerName parameter and a
        help message that explains the expected parameter value.

 
        Param
          (
            [parameter(mandatory=$true,
                       HelpMessage="Enter one or more computer names separated by commas.")]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


  Alias Attribute

      The Alias attribute establishes an alternate name for the parameter. There 
      is no limit to the number of aliases that you can assign to a parameter. 

      The following example shows a parameter declaration that adds the "CN" and
      "MachineName" aliases to the mandatory ComputerName parameter.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [alias("CN","MachineName")]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


  Parameter and Variable Validation Attributes

      Validation attributes direct Windows PowerShell to test the parameter
      values that users submit when they call the advanced function. If the parameter
      values fail the test, an error is generated and the function is not called. You
      can also use some of the validation attributes to restrict the values that users
      can specify for variables.



    AllowNull Validation Attribute

        The AllowNull attribute allows the value of a mandatory parameter
        to be null ($null). The following example declares a ComputerName parameter
        that can have a Null value.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [AllowNull()]
            [String]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    AllowEmptyString Validation Attribute

        The AllowEmptyString attribute allows the value of a mandatory parameter to be
        an empty string (""). The following example declares a ComputerName parameter
        that can have an empty string value.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [AllowEmptyString()]
            [String]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    AllowEmptyCollection Validation Attribute

        The AllowEmptyCollection attribute allows the value of a mandatory parameter
        to be an empty collection (@()). The following example declares a ComputerName
        parameter that can have a empty collection value.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [AllowEmptyCollection()]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    ValidateCount Validation Attribute

        The ValidateCount attribute specifies the minimum and maximum number
        of parameter values that a parameter accepts. Windows PowerShell
        generates an error if the number of parameter values in the command that
        calls the function is outside that range. 

        The following parameter declaration creates a ComputerName parameter that
        takes 1 to 5 parameter values.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidateCount(1,5)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 


    ValidateLength Validation Attribute

        The ValidateLength attribute specifies the minimum and maximum number 
        of characters in a parameter or variable value. Windows PowerShell generates an
        error if the length of a value specified for a parameter or a variable
        is outside of the range.

        In the following example, each computer name must have one to 10
        characters. 

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidateLength(1,10)]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 

        In the following example, the value of the variable $number must be a
        minimum of one character in length, and a maximum of ten characters.

        [Int32][ValidateLength(1,10)]$number = 01
 

    ValidatePattern Validation Attribute

        The ValidatePattern attribute specifies a regular expression that
        is compared to the parameter or variable value. Windows PowerShell generates
        an error if the value does not match the regular expression 
        pattern. 

        In the following example, the parameter value must be a four-digit
        number, and each digit must be a number 0 to 9.  

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidatePattern("[0-9][0-9][0-9][0-9]")]
            [String[]]
            $ComputerName
          ) 

        In the following example, the value of the variable $number must be a
        four-digit number, and each digit must be a number 0 to 9.

        [Int32][ValidatePattern("[0-9][0-9][0-9][0-9]")]$number = 1111

    ValidateRange Validation Attribute

        The ValidateRange attribute specifies a numeric range for each
        parameter or variable value. Windows PowerShell generates an error
        if any value is outside that range. In the following example,
        the value of the Attempts parameter must be between 0 and 10.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidateRange(0,10)]
            [Int]
            $Attempts
          ) 

        In the following example, the value of the variable $number must be 
        between 0 and 10.

        [Int32][ValidateRange(0,10)]$number = 5
 

    ValidateScript Validation Attribute

        The ValidateScript attribute specifies a script that is used 
        to validate a parameter or variable value. Windows PowerShell
        pipes the value to the script, and generates an error if the
        script returns "false" or if the script throws an exception.

        When you use the ValidateScript attribute, the value
        that is being validated is mapped to the $_ variable. You can
        use the $_ variable to refer to the value in the script.
        
        In the following example, the value of the EventDate parameter
        must be greater than or equal to the current date.

        Param
          (
            [parameter()]
            [ValidateScript({$_ -ge (get-date)})]
            [DateTime]
            $EventDate
          ) 


       In the following example, the value of the variable $date must be
       greater than or equal to the current date and time.

       [DateTime][ValidateScript({$_ -ge (get-date)})]$date = (get-date)

    ValidateSet Attribute

        The ValidateSet attribute specifies a set of valid values for a 
        parameter or variable. Windows PowerShell generates an error if a
        parameter or variable value does not match a value in the set. In
        the following example, the value of the Detail parameter can only
        be "Low," "Average," or "High."

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidateSet("Low", "Average", "High")]
            [String[]]
            $Detail
          ) 

        In the following example, the value of the variable $flavor must be 
        either Chocolate, Strawberry, or Vanilla.

        [String][ValidateSet("Chocolate", "Strawberry", "Vanilla")]$flavor = Strawberry

 

    ValidateNotNull Validation Attribute

        The ValidateNotNull attribute specifies that the parameter
        value cannot be null ($null). Windows PowerShell generates an
        error if the parameter value is null. 

        The ValidateNotNull attribute is designed to be used when the
        type of the parameter value is not specified or when the specified
        type will accept a value of Null. (If you specify a type that will
        not accept a null value, such as a string, the null value will be
        rejected without the ValidateNotNull attribute, because it does not
        match the specified type.)  
        
        In the following example, the value of the ID parameter
        cannot be null.

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidateNotNull()]
            $ID
          ) 


    ValidateNotNullOrEmpty Validation Attribute

        The ValidateNotNullOrEmpty attribute specifies that the parameter 
        value cannot be null ($null) and cannot be an empty string ("").
        Windows PowerShell generates an error if the parameter is used in 
        a function call, but its value is null, an empty string, or an empty
        array.   

        Param
          (
            [parameter(Mandatory=$true)]
            [ValidateNotNullOrEmpty()]
            [String[]]
            $UserName
          ) 


 Dynamic Parameters 

    Dynamic parameters are parameters of a cmdlet, function, or script
    that are available only under certain conditions. 

    For example, several provider cmdlets have parameters that are
    available only when the cmdlet is used in the provider drive, or in
    a particular path of the provider drive. For example, the Encoding
    parameter is available on the Add-Content, Get-Content, and Set-Content
    cmdlets only when it is used in a file system drive.

    You can also create a parameter that appears only when another parameter
    is used in the function command or when another parameter has a certain
    value.

    Dynamic parameters can be very useful, but use them only when necessary,
    because they can be difficult for users to discover. To find a dynamic
    parameter, the user must be in the provider path, use the ArgumentList
    parameter of the Get-Command cmdlet, or use the Path parameter of Get-Help.

    To create a dynamic parameter for a function or script, use the 
    DynamicParam keyword.

    The syntax is as follows:

      DynamicParam {<statement-list>} 

    In the statement list, use an If statement to specify the
    conditions under which the parameter is available in the function.

    Use the New-Object cmdlet to create a 
    System.Management.Automation.RuntimeDefinedParameter object to 
    represent the parameter and specify its name. 

    You can also use a New-Object command to create a 
    System.Management.Automation.ParameterAttribute object to represent
    attributes of the parameter, such as Mandatory, Position, or
    ValueFromPipeline or its parameter set.

    The following example shows a sample function with standard 
    parameters named Name and Path, and an optional dynamic parameter
    named DP1.The DP1 parameter is in the PSet1 parameter set and has
    a type of Int32. The DP1 parameter is available in the Sample
    function only when the value of the Path parameter contains "HKLM:",
    indicating that it is being used in the HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE registry
    drive.
 

    function Get-Sample {
        [CmdletBinding()]
        Param ([String]$Name, [String]$Path)
 
        DynamicParam
        {
            if ($path -match ".*HKLM.*:")
            {
                $attributes = new-object System.Management.Automation.ParameterAttribute
                $attributes.ParameterSetName = "__AllParameterSets"
                $attributes.Mandatory = $false
                $attributeCollection = new-object `
                    -Type System.Collections.ObjectModel.Collection[System.Attribute]
                $attributeCollection.Add($attributes)

                $dynParam1 = new-object `
                    -Type System.Management.Automation.RuntimeDefinedParameter("dp1", [Int32], $attributeCollection)
            
                $paramDictionary = new-object `
                    -Type System.Management.Automation.RuntimeDefinedParameterDictionary
                $paramDictionary.Add("dp1", $dynParam1)
                return $paramDictionary
            }
        }
    }


    For more information, see "RuntimeDefinedParameter Class" in 
    the MSDN (Microsoft Developer Network) library at
    http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkID=145130.        

  Switch Parameters
    Switch parameters are parameters with no parameter value. They
    are effective only when they are used and have only one effect.

    For example, the -NoProfile parameter of PowerShell.exe is
    a switch parameter.

    To create a switch parameter in a function, specify the Switch type
    in the parameter definition.
    
    For example:
        Param ([Switch]<ParameterName>)
    -or- 
        Param
          (
             [parameter(Mandatory=$false)]
             [Switch]
             $<ParameterName>
          )

    Switch parameters are easy to use and are preferred over Boolean
    parameters, which have a more difficult syntax.

    For example, to use a switch parameter, the user types the parameter
    in the command.    
        -IncludeAll

    To use a Boolean parameter, the user types the parameter and a Boolean
    value.
        -IncludeAll:$true
 
    When creating switch parameters, choose the parameter name carefully.
    Be sure that the parameter name communicates the effect of the parameter
    to the user, and avoid ambiguous terms, such as Filter or Maximum, that
    might imply that a value is required.



SEE ALSO
    about_Functions
    about_Functions_Advanced
    about_Functions_Advanced_Methods
    about_Functions_CmdletBindingAttribute
    about_Functions_OutputTypeAttribute














